<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Gianluca Russo</title>
    <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://gianlucarusso.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/images/icon_hud3c4f4215db4e1df4afdcacbbae4761e_411935_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>International Political Economy</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ipe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a third year undergraduate class at Cunef on International Political Economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ### Boston University Summer 2019

- [CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics](https://gianlucarusso.github.io/JMP/Syll_EC204_SMR2_2019.pdf) (Evaluations available upon request)

### Boston University Summer 2018

- [CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics](https://gianlucarusso.github.io/JMP/Syll_EC204_SMR2_2019.pdf) (Evaluations available upon request) --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nation-Building through Restorative Justice (2026)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/trc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/trc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  
 How do societies rebuild after decades of institutionalized oppression and intergroup violence? We address this question by studying the South African Truth and Reconciliation Commission (TRC), which sought to rebuild the nation by publicly documenting human rights violations committed under apartheid. Using quasi-exogenous variation in exposure to live TRC broadcasts, we show that the TRC strengthened unity among Black South Africans, reducing interethnic violence and increasing national identification. At the same time, it weakened interracial relations, increasing segregation and reducing intermarriage. Content analysis of the hearings suggests that intra-Black reconciliation---driven by emotional resonance rather than informational updating---was the key mechanism behind Black unity. Finally, using administrative tax data, we show that these heightened racial divisions had negative downstream consequences: TRC exposure reduced the effectiveness of affirmative action policies aimed at redressing apartheid-era discrimination.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity and Conflict in New Democracies</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/sa_xeno/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/sa_xeno/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 
## Abstract

&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  How do states rebuild nations after a major conflict? Truth and Reconciliation Commissions (TRCs) have emerged as one of the most common interventions to achieve this objective. Despite their popularity, little is known about their efficacy to foster reconciliation and nation-building. We fill this gap by studying the seminal TRC established in South Africa after the end of Apartheid. To measure exposure to TRC across South African municipalities, we leverage quasi random variation in media coverage of the TRC message. South African municipalities with higher historical exposure to TRC on media have lower levels of violence today. This effect is driven by improved nation-building and higher trust towards post-Apartheid institutions. Exploiting daily variation in TRC hearings and mediatic exposure in the short-run, we bolster our interpretation that our long-run results are forged in the years of the TRC activity. The same evidence suggests that our results are driven by the coverage of TRC on media as opposed to generic media exposure. --&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ideology, Conformity and Performance</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/fasci_demia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/fasci_demia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 
## Abstract

&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  How do states rebuild nations after a major conflict? Truth and Reconciliation Commissions (TRCs) have emerged as one of the most common interventions to achieve this objective. Despite their popularity, little is known about their efficacy to foster reconciliation and nation-building. We fill this gap by studying the seminal TRC established in South Africa after the end of Apartheid. To measure exposure to TRC across South African municipalities, we leverage quasi random variation in media coverage of the TRC message. South African municipalities with higher historical exposure to TRC on media have lower levels of violence today. This effect is driven by improved nation-building and higher trust towards post-Apartheid institutions. Exploiting daily variation in TRC hearings and mediatic exposure in the short-run, we bolster our interpretation that our long-run results are forged in the years of the TRC activity. The same evidence suggests that our results are driven by the coverage of TRC on media as opposed to generic media exposure. --&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Socializing Alone: How Online Homophily Has Undermined Social Cohesion in the US (2026)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/facebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  Online social networks have changed how people interact across large distances. We examine the long-run effect of a key feature of these networks – online homophily – on interpersonal interactions in local communities. Using Facebook data, we measure online homophily across counties in the United States. To identify effects, we exploit a conflict between Facebook and Google over data sharing of user information in the early expansion phase of Facebook, which induced variation in the ability to connect with friends in socially similar counties. We find evidence that homophilic connections led to increased Facebook usage but reduced offline socialization, as measured by visits to bars, restaurants, and live sports events. The effects are substantial: we estimate that a one-standard deviation increase in online homophily led to a 60-70% long-run increase in social media usage and approximately a 25% reduction in offine socialization. This shift was accompanied by a deterioration of local social cohesion, as individuals became less connected across income strata and less likely to share the same political opinions with others in their counties. Overall, our results indicate that when a natural demand for connecting with socially similar people is met by the supply of a &#39;death-of-distance&#39; technology, it comes at the cost of social cohesion and traditional community bonds at the local level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outmigration and Economic Development: Evidence from the Italian Mass Migration (2025)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/outmigration/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/outmigration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  Does emigration affect economic development? We study this question in the context of the Italian mass emigration between 1884 and 1913, when twelve million Italians left the country.
We assemble a unique dataset at the municipality level, linking cumulative emigration rates to a number of indicators of economic development throughout the twentieth century.
Exploiting variation in the availability of information about the potential gains from migration before the start of mass migration, we construct an instrumental variable for the total emigration rate.
Results indicate that while instrumented cumulative emigration was balanced on population before the start of mass emigration, it had a negative, large, and highly persistent effect on short and long run population. Historical mass emigration also reduced educational attainment, income per capita and other proxies of economic development in the long run. Further, we show that emigration favored the expansion of the agricultural sector, at the expense of manufacturing. We speculate that selective emigration was a key mechanism behind our results.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Media and Assimilation: Evidence from the Golden Age of Radio (2025)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/radio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/radio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt; The advent of the radio networks in the early twentieth century marked the inception
of the first national media platform in US history. This development coincided
with the conclusion of the Age of Mass Migration, a historical period characterized by
record-high diversity within the US society. How did the sudden rise of national radio
networks affect the assimilation of millions of immigrants in the US? I answer this
question by building quasi-random variation in the initial expansion of radio networks
coverage. Through the application of a difference-in-difference design and leveraging
evidence from diverse samples, I document that higher exposure to radio networks
facilitated immigrant assimilation across various outcomes, including higher rates of
intermarriage with natives, increased naturalization, and a greater propensity to adopt
names that sounded less foreign. Additionally, I find that exposure to radio networks
led to enhanced English proficiency among recently arrived immigrants. I argue that a
key channel of assimilation was through the impact of role models on the media. Using
data on baseball, I show that immigrants perceived baseball players as media role
models of assimilation. Immigrant households were more likely to name their children
after baseball players who shared similar ancestral origins to them or who achieved
notable success during a season.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inequality and Conflict: The Long-Run Legacy of the Reconquesta (2025)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/class/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  We study how historical inequality shape long-run political preferences. Our setting is Catalonia, where Christian counts expanded southward into Al-Andalus between the ninth and eleventh centuries at heterogeneous speeds, creating a frontier whose location was driven by idiosyncratic military events. Using a spatial regression discontinuity design comparing municipalities on either side of this frontier, we find that areas conquered more rapidly display persistently stronger support for the radical left. Southern municipalities show higher vote shares for radical-left parties in all democratic elections since 1977, a greater historical presence of anarcho-syndicalist and communist organizations, and more frequent protest activity. These patterns extend back to the Second Republic and the Spanish Civil War, including differences in militias, collectivization, and repression. We trace these effects to the resettlement process in fast-conquered territories, which produced concentrated landholding, weaker state capacity, and a large class of landless peasants. Our findings show how inequality under weak political authority can generate lasting radical political identities.
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>War, Socialism and the Rise of Fascism: An Empirical Exploration (2022)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/project/wwi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/project/wwi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  The recent ascent of right-wing populist movements in many countries has rekindled interest in understanding the causes of the rise of Fascism in inter-war years. In this paper, we argue that there was a strong link between the surge of support for the Socialist Party after World War I (WWI) and the subsequent emergence of Fascism in Italy. We first develop a source of variation in socialist support across Italian municipalities in the 1919 election based on war casualties from the area. We show that these casualties are unrelated to a battery of political, economic and social variables before the war and had a major impact on socialist support (partly because the Socialists were the main anti-war political movement). Our main result is that this boost to socialist support (that is “exogenous” to the prior political leaning of the municipality) led to greater local fascist activity as measured by local party branches and fascist political violence (squadrismo), and to significantly larger vote share of the Fascist Party in the 1921 and 1924 elections. We also provide evidence that landowner associations and greater presence of local elites played an important role in the rise of Fascism. Finally, we find greater likelihood of Jewish deportations in 1943-45 and lower vote share for Christian Democrats after World War II in areas with greater early fascist activity.
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulating Child Labor: Evidence from the US Progressive Era (2020)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/cll/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/cll/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  From 1880 to 1920, child labor in the United States fell dramatically. At the same time, most states passed laws regulating minimum working ages and mandating compulsory schooling laws. Past quantitative work based on census samples have yielded mixed results on the efficacy of these laws and historians have questioned whether the politically powerful employers of children would allow such regulation if child labor was in high demand. Turning to the newly-digitized complete count census data from 1880, 1900, 1910, 1920, and 1930, we find large effects of child labor laws and compulsory schooling laws on child labor. While Progressive era legislation reduced labor supply from boys and girls in equal measure, the laws did had differential effects, binding in urban areas especially in the largest cities and more for the children of foreign-born parents. Children with parents working in manufacturing and textiles were especially affected by the labor restrictions.
In contrast to the reduction of labor supply among white children in urban areas, we find that legislation had mixed effects on the odds of children not explicitly targeted by the reformers, in particular rural white and black children.
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Italian WWI Fatality List</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/wwi_cas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/wwi_cas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- After WWI The Italian Ministry of War allocated substantial financial resources to gather, organize and analyze large amount of data on the conflict. The Ministry hired the most prominent scholars and utilized Powers and Hollerit accounting machines to process the data for the first time in history. Although with some discrepancies, Giorgio Mortara and Corrado Gini worked up to conclude that approximately 650,000 Italian soldiers died during or immediately after the conflict. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the state propaganda, the Fascist regime organized a massive data collection on the identity of all the military personnel who died during WWI. The goal of the propaganda was to manufacture a narrative that would legitimate and place the birth of Fascism among the battlefields of the war. To do so, the Ministry allocated substantial resources to the task. It hired the most prominent statisticians and utilized Powers and Hollerit accounting machines to process data for the first time in Italian history. Although with some discrepancies, Giorgio Mortara and Corrado Gini worked up to conclude that approximately 650,000 Italian soldiers died during or immediately after the conflict.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sources used to piece the records together were multiple. These encompassed data from the various statistical offices of the army and the Ministry of War, records from Italian municipalities and data from the Italian and Austrian Red Cross. The Ministry started the publication of the first roll of honor in 1926. Comprising 28 volumes, the publication was concluded only in 1964. Each volume lists the fatalities by Italian macro regions. Among the information included are the municipality and data of birth, rank and unit at time of death, cause and place of death. The historical municipality of birth refers to the name of the municipality as it appeared on the drafting cards, hence approximately the end of the nineteenth century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can search individual records on different websites. However, the most comprehensive one is probably 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cadutigrandeguerra.it/CercaNome.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;cadutigrandeguerra.it&lt;/a&gt;. It is curated by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.istoreco.re.it&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Istoreco&lt;/a&gt;: the Institute for the history of the Resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;bottom.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historical Demographer 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://fornasin.weebly.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Alessio Fornasin&lt;/a&gt; has written a lot about the different estimates of WWI Italian fatalities. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AM Radio Coverage</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/radio_propagation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/radio_propagation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- *cool cite*. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Golden Age of Radio in the United States signed a revolution of media access in the country.
&lt;img align=&#34;right&#34; src=&#34;wells.png&#34;&gt;
To study the effect of radio on American society during the interwar period I coded in R a model of ground wave propagation that, given the characteristics of the transmitting antenna and the distance of the receiver outputs the signal strength of the ground wave.
The model takes into accounts ground conductivity that is the most important factor that affects the attenuation of the ground wave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
Below the coverage of NBC in 1940 in the US at day time.

![NBC coverage]() --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technical details of AM radio propagation and the way I implemented the model are available 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gianlucarusso.github.io/gianlucarusso_radio_appendix.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I am turning the code I wrote into an R package that will be available for download on Github soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/cas204/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/cas204/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have designed and taught EC 204 at Boston University as an Instructor during summer 2018 and summer 2019. The class focuses on the basics of linear regression analysis and hypothesis testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ### Boston University Summer 2019

- [CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics](https://gianlucarusso.github.io/JMP/Syll_EC204_SMR2_2019.pdf) (Evaluations available upon request)

### Boston University Summer 2018

- [CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics](https://gianlucarusso.github.io/JMP/Syll_EC204_SMR2_2019.pdf) (Evaluations available upon request) --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resesarch</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/teaching/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
