<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Gianluca Russo</title>
    <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://gianlucarusso.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/images/icon_hud3c4f4215db4e1df4afdcacbbae4761e_411935_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>War, Socialism and the Rise of Fascism: An Empirical Exploration (2021)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/project/wwi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/project/wwi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recent ascent of right-wing populist movements in many countries has rekindled interest in understanding the causes of the rise of Fascism in inter-war years. In this paper, we argue that there was a strong link between the surge of support for the Socialist Party after World War I (WWI) and the subsequent emergence of Fascism in Italy. We first develop a source of variation in socialist support across Italian municipalities in the 1919 election based on war casualties from the area. We show that these casualties are unrelated to a battery of political, economic and social variables before the war and had a major impact on socialist support (partly because the Socialists were the main anti-war political movement). Our main result is that this boost to socialist support (that is “exogenous” to the prior political leaning of the municipality) led to greater local fascist activity as measured by local party branches and fascist political violence (squadrismo), and to significantly larger vote share of the Fascist Party in the 1921 and 1924 elections. We also provide evidence that landowner associations and greater presence of local elites played an important role in the rise of Fascism. Finally, we find greater likelihood of Jewish deportations in 1943-45 and lower vote share for Christian Democrats after World War II in areas with greater early fascist activity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Media and Assimilation: Evidence from the Golden Age of Radio (2021)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/radio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/radio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I argue that exposure to mainstream mass media facilitates immigrants&amp;rsquo; assimilation. I exploit the rise and expansion of radio broadcasting in the United States after the Age of Mass Migration ended to identify the effect of radio exposure on immigrants&amp;rsquo; assimilation.
I reconstruct exogenous exposure to radio networks using a novel propagation model suitable to AM radio, the only radio technology available at the time.
Exploiting the US full count census, I find that radio networks had a strong effect on immigrants&amp;rsquo; assimilation. Immigrants exposed to radio networks exerted higher effort to assimilate by naming their children with less distinctively foreign names and by becoming US citizens more often. Exposure to US radio networks also increased the likelihood of marrying a US citizen from US-born parents. Using names from baseball players, I show that aspiration might have been a key mechanism to explain why radio promoted assimilation. Immigrant households named their children exclusively after players that performed particularly well during the season, suggesting they were &amp;lsquo;&amp;lsquo;naming for success.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Echo Chambers: Does Online Network Structure Affect Political Polarization?</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/facebook/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Economic Effects of Post-Conflict Reconciliation: Evidence from South Africa</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/trc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/trc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outmigration and Economic Development: Evidence from the Italian Mass Migration</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/outmigration/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/outmigration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!---
## Abstract

Does emigration affect economic development? We study this question in the context of the Italian mass emigration between 1884 and 1913, when twelve million Italians left the country.
We assemble a unique dataset at the municipality level, linking cumulative emigration rates to a number of indicators of economic development throughout the twentieth century.
Exploiting variation in the availability of information about the potential gains from migration before the start of mass migration, we construct an instrumental variable for the total emigration rate.
Results indicate that while instrumented cumulative emigration was balanced on population before the start of mass emigration, it had a negative, large, and highly persistent effect on short and long run population. Historical mass emigration also reduced educational attainment, income per capita and other proxies of economic development in the long run. Further, we show that emigration favored the expansion of the agricultural sector, at the expense of manufacturing. We speculate that selective emigration was a key mechanism behind our results.
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulating Child Labor: Evidence from the US Progressive Era (2020)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/cll/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/cll/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1880 to 1920, child labor in the United States fell dramatically. At the same time, most states passed laws regulating minimum working ages and mandating compulsory schooling laws. Past quantitative work based on census samples have yielded mixed results on the efficacy of these laws and historians have questioned whether the politically powerful employers of children would allow such regulation if child labor was in high demand. Turning to the newly-digitized complete count census data from 1880, 1900, 1910, 1920, and 1930, we find large effects of child labor laws and compulsory schooling laws on child labor. While Progressive era legislation reduced labor supply from boys and girls in equal measure, the laws did had differential effects, binding in urban areas especially in the largest cities and more for the children of foreign-born parents. Children with parents working in manufacturing and textiles were especially affected by the labor restrictions.
In contrast to the reduction of labor supply among white children in urban areas, we find that legislation had mixed effects on the odds of children not explicitly targeted by the reformers, in particular rural white and black children.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Italian WWI Fatality List</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/wwi_cas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/wwi_cas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- After WWI The Italian Ministry of War allocated substantial financial resources to gather, organize and analyze large amount of data on the conflict. The Ministry hired the most prominent scholars and utilized Powers and Hollerit accounting machines to process the data for the first time in history. Although with some discrepancies, Giorgio Mortara and Corrado Gini worked up to conclude that approximately 650,000 Italian soldiers died during or immediately after the conflict. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the state propaganda, the Fascist regime organized a massive data collection on the identity of all the military personnel who died during WWI. The goal of the propaganda was to manufacture a narrative that would legitimate and place the birth of Fascism among the battlefields of the war. To do so, the Ministry allocated substantial resources to the task. It hired the most prominent statisticians and utilized Powers and Hollerit accounting machines to process data for the first time in Italian history. Although with some discrepancies, Giorgio Mortara and Corrado Gini worked up to conclude that approximately 650,000 Italian soldiers died during or immediately after the conflict.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sources used to piece the records together were multiple. These encompassed data from the various statistical offices of the army and the Ministry of War, records from Italian municipalities and data from the Italian and Austrian Red Cross. The Ministry started the publication of the first roll of honor in 1926. Comprising 28 volumes, the publication was concluded only in 1964. Each volume lists the fatalities by Italian macro regions. Among the information included are the municipality and data of birth, rank and unit at time of death, cause and place of death. The historical municipality of birth refers to the name of the municipality as it appeared on the drafting cards, hence approximately the end of the nineteenth century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can search individual records on different websites. However, the most comprehensive one is probably 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cadutigrandeguerra.it/CercaNome.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;cadutigrandeguerra.it&lt;/a&gt;. It is curated by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.istoreco.re.it&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Istoreco&lt;/a&gt;: the Institute for the history of the Resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;bottom.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historical Demographer 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://fornasin.weebly.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Alessio Fornasin&lt;/a&gt; has written a lot about the different estimates of WWI Italian fatalities. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AM Radio Coverage</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/radio_propagation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/radio_propagation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- *cool cite*. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Golden Age of Radio in the United States signed a revolution of media access in the country.
&lt;img align=&#34;right&#34; src=&#34;wells.png&#34;&gt;
To study the effect of radio on American society during the interwar period I coded in R a model of ground wave propagation that, given the characteristics of the transmitting antenna and the distance of the receiver outputs the signal strength of the ground wave.
The model takes into accounts ground conductivity that is the most important factor that affects the attenuation of the ground wave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
Below the coverage of NBC in 1940 in the US at day time.

![NBC coverage]() --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technical details of AM radio propagation and the way I implemented the model are available 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gianlucarusso.github.io/gianlucarusso_radio_appendix.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I am turning the code I wrote into an R package that will be available for download on Github soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/cas204/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/cas204/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have designed and taught EC 204 at Boston University as an Instructor during summer 2018 and summer 2019. The class focuses on the basics of linear regression analysis and hypothesis testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send me an email if you are interested in seeing the evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ### Boston University Summer 2019

- [CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics](https://gianlucarusso.github.io/JMP/Syll_EC204_SMR2_2019.pdf) (Evaluations available upon request)

### Boston University Summer 2018

- [CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics](https://gianlucarusso.github.io/JMP/Syll_EC204_SMR2_2019.pdf) (Evaluations available upon request) --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAS EC 102 Introduction to Macroeconomics</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec102/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec102/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During Grad School I have been a teaching fellow for Introduction to Macroeconomics. I worked with Instructor Bruce Watson and my duties included teaching discussion sessions and grading exams. Send me an email for evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAS EC 201 Introduction to Microeconomics</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec201/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec201/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During my second year at BU I was also a teaching fellow for Introductory Micro. For this class I graded assignments, final exams and held office hours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAS EC 371 Environmental Economics</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec371/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec371/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During my second year at BU I was a teaching fellow for Environmental Economics. The class was taught by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/johannesschmieder/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Johannes Schmieder&lt;/a&gt;. My duties included teaching a review of analysis applied to economics, grading and holding office hours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resesarch</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/teaching/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
