<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gianluca Russo</title>
    <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://gianlucarusso.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Gianluca Russo</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 14:42:45 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/images/icon_hu98c83ca92acbb120fc78fd5a852db45d_58224_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Gianluca Russo</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>WWI and the rise of Fascism in Italy: Evidence from La Vittoria Mutilata</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/wwi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/wwi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key steps that allowed Mussolini to become the Italian Duce was the victory in the 1924 national elections. I study the impact of World War I on Mussolini&amp;rsquo;s electoral success. To gauge the effect of the war, I construct a measure of military casualties from the universe of Italian municipalities, which is matched to municipal level voting in the 1924 election. Controlling for the number of military drafted in an Italian municipality, variation in the share of casualties is induced by military events exogenous to municipality characteristics that could simultaneously affect support for Fascism. Using this conditional independence approach, I find that a higher share of casualties increases the vote share for Fascism. More than half of the increase in the vote share for Mussolini is matched by a decrease in the vote share of the Socialist party. I decompose the effect of the casualties rate by its intensity to show that the number of casualties interacted positively with the number of veterans back from the frontline. I interpret this as evidence that Fascist support was driven by municipalities where the high number of casualties was matched by veterans militarized and brutalized by the war experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mass Media and Cultural Assimilation: Broadcasting the American Dream on Radio</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/radio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/radio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does media shape culture? I leverage the expansion of radio networks in the United States to identify the impact of access to mass media on cultural assimilation and homogenization. I reconstruct radio network access via a signal propagation model suitable to AM radio, the only radio technology available at the time. I determine what radio channels were available to American households by feeding the propagation model with newly digitized data on the universe of transmitting stations during the interwar period. I combine radio network coverage with several measures of cultural change based on naming patterns for children. Exploiting exogenous variation in radio signal reception induced by soil characteristics and stations&amp;rsquo; tower growth over time, I provide evidence that network access homogenized American culture. Homogenization occurred through the assimilation of white immigrant and black households towards mainstream white native culture. Assimilation is strongest for immigrant families: foreign parents were six percent more likely to name their sons using popular white names after network access. Focusing on names from baseball players, I suggest that aspirational naming is a key mechanism to explain certain features of the results. While foreign households picked from the full distribution of baseball names, native families chose names exclusively from the most successful, those featured in the All-Star games. Thus, in addition to diffusing information, the radio has subtler effects, increasing the likelihood of &amp;ldquo;naming for success&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulating Child Labor: Evidence from the US Progressive Era</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/cll/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/cll/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1880 to 1920, child labor in the United States fell dramatically. At the same time, most states passed laws regulating minimum working ages. Past quantitative work based on census samples have yielded mixed results on the efficacy of these laws and historians have questioned whether the politically powerful employers of children would allow such regulation if child labor was in high demand. Turning to the newly-digitized complete count census data from 1880, 1900, 1910, 1920, and 1930, we find large effects of child labor laws on child labor. While the laws reduced labor from boys and girls in equal measure, the laws did had differential effects, binding in urban areas not rural and especially in the largest cities and more for the children of foreign-born parents. Children with parents working in manufacturing and textiles were especially affected by the labor restrictions. In contrast to the reduction of labor supply among white children, child labor laws had limited effects on the odds of African American boys or girls working.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 14:42:45 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;page-under-construction&#34;&gt;Page under construction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I want to post data I digitize or info on datasets&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/cas204/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/cas204/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have designed and taught EC 204 at Boston University as an Instructor during summer 2018 and summer 2019. The class focuses on the basics of linear regression analysis and hypothesis testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send me an email if you are interested in seeing the evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ### Boston University Summer 2019

- [CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics](https://gianlucarusso.github.io/JMP/Syll_EC204_SMR2_2019.pdf) (Evaluations available upon request)

### Boston University Summer 2018

- [CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics](https://gianlucarusso.github.io/JMP/Syll_EC204_SMR2_2019.pdf) (Evaluations available upon request) --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resesarch</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/teaching/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
