<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gianluca Russo</title>
    <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://gianlucarusso.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Gianluca Russo</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/images/icon_hue82af429582e6f2ab175ca8e020ad14c_1706_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Gianluca Russo</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulating Child Labor: Evidence from the US Progressive Era</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/cll/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/cll/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1880 to 1920, child labor in the United States fell dramatically. At the same time, most states passed laws regulating minimum working ages and mandating compulsory schooling laws. Past quantitative work based on census samples have yielded mixed results on the efficacy of these laws and historians have questioned whether the politically powerful employers of children would allow such regulation if child labor was in high demand. Turning to the newly-digitized complete count census data from 1880, 1900, 1910, 1920, and 1930, we find large effects of child labor laws and compulsory schooling laws on child labor. While Progressive era legislation reduced labor supply from boys and girls in equal measure, the laws did had differential effects, binding in urban areas especially in the largest cities and more for the children of foreign-born parents. Children with parents working in manufacturing and textiles were especially affected by the labor restrictions.
In contrast to the reduction of labor supply among white children in urban areas, we find that legislation had mixed effects on the odds of children not explicitly targeted by the reformers, in particular rural white and black children.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WWI and the rise of Fascism in Italy</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/wwi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/wwi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key steps that allowed Mussolini to become the Italian &lt;em&gt;Duce&lt;/em&gt; was the victory in the 1924 national elections.
I study the impact of World War I on Mussolini&amp;rsquo;s electoral success. I reconstruct the military death rate for the universe of Italian municipalities, which is matched to municipal level voting in the 1924 election.
Controlling for the number of military drafted in an Italian municipality, variation in the share of fatalities is induced by military events exogenous to municipality characteristics that could simultaneously affect support for Fascism.
I find that a higher share of fatalities increases the vote share for Fascism. More than half of the increase in the vote share for Mussolini is matched by a decrease in the vote share of the Socialist party.
I decompose my analysis by the intensity of the fatality rate to show persuasive evidence that the number of fatalities interacted positively with the number of veterans back from the frontline. I show that the effect of fatalities is driven by municipalities that in 1921 had above median vote shares for the Socialist party.
This is consistent with historical narratives arguing that the initial rise of Mussolini was facilitated and acclaimed by the &amp;ldquo;red menace&amp;rdquo;, i.e. the fear of a Socialist revolution in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Italian World War One Fatality List</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/wwi_cas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/wwi_cas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- After WWI The Italian Ministry of War allocated substantial financial resources to gather, organize and analyze large amount of data on the conflict. The Ministry hired the most prominent scholars and utilized Powers and Hollerit accounting machines to process the data for the first time in history. Although with some discrepancies, Giorgio Mortara and Corrado Gini worked up to conclude that approximately 650,000 Italian soldiers died during or immediately after the conflict. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the state propaganda, the Fascist regime organized a massive data collection on the identity of all the military personnel who died during WWI. The goal of the propaganda was to manufacture a narrative that would legitimate and place the birth of Fascism among the battlefields of the war. To do so, the Ministry allocated substantial resources to the task. It hired the most prominent statisticians and utilized Powers and Hollerit accounting machines to process data for the first time in Italian history. Although with some discrepancies, Giorgio Mortara and Corrado Gini worked up to conclude that approximately 650,000 Italian soldiers died during or immediately after the conflict.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sources used to piece the records together were multiple. These encompassed data from the various statistical offices of the army and the Ministry of War, records from Italian municipalities and data from the Italian and Austrian Red Cross. The Ministry started the publication of the first roll of honor in 1926. Comprising 28 volumes, the publication was concluded only in 1964. Each volume lists the fatalities by Italian macro regions. Among the information included are the municipality and data of birth, rank and unit at time of death, cause and place of death. The historical municipality of birth refers to the name of the municipality as it appeared on the drafting cards, hence approximately the end of the nineteenth century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can search individual records on different websites. However, the most comprehensive one is probably 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cadutigrandeguerra.it/CercaNome.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;cadutigrandeguerra.it&lt;/a&gt;. It is curated by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.istoreco.re.it&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Istoreco&lt;/a&gt;: the Institute for the history of the Resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;bottom.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historical Demographer 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://fornasin.weebly.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Alessio Fornasin&lt;/a&gt; has written a lot about the different estimates of WWI Italian fatalities. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AM Radio Coverage</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/radio_propagation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data_projects/radio_propagation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- *cool cite*. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Golden Age of Radio in the United States signed a revolution of media access in the country.
&lt;img align=&#34;right&#34; src=&#34;wells.png&#34;&gt;
To study the effect of radio on American society during the interwar period I coded in R a model of ground wave propagation that, given the characteristics of the transmitting antenna and the distance of the receiver outputs the signal strength of the ground wave.
The model takes into accounts ground conductivity that is the most important factor that affects the attenuation of the ground wave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
Below the coverage of NBC in 1940 in the US at day time.

![NBC coverage]() --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technical details of AM radio propagation and the way I implemented the model are available 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gianlucarusso.github.io/gianlucarusso_radio_appendix.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I am turning the code I wrote into an R package that will be available for download on Github soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mass Media and Cultural Assimilation: Broadcasting the American Dream on Radio</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/radio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/radio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does media shape culture? I leverage the expansion of radio networks in the United States to identify the impact of access to mass media on cultural assimilation and homogenization. I reconstruct radio network access via a signal propagation model suitable to AM radio, the only radio technology available at the time. I determine what radio channels were available to American households by feeding the propagation model with newly digitized data on the universe of transmitting stations during the interwar period. I combine radio network coverage with several measures of cultural change based on naming patterns for children. Exploiting exogenous variation in radio signal reception induced by soil characteristics and stations&amp;rsquo; tower growth over time, I provide evidence that network access homogenized American culture. Homogenization occurred through the assimilation of white immigrant and black households towards mainstream white native culture. Assimilation is strongest for immigrant families: foreign parents were six percent more likely to name their sons using popular white names after network access. Focusing on names from baseball players, I suggest that aspirational naming is a key mechanism to explain certain features of the results. While foreign households picked from the full distribution of baseball names, native families chose names exclusively from the most successful, those featured in the All-Star games. Thus, in addition to diffusing information, the radio has subtler effects, increasing the likelihood of &amp;ldquo;naming for success&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/cas204/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/cas204/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have designed and taught EC 204 at Boston University as an Instructor during summer 2018 and summer 2019. The class focuses on the basics of linear regression analysis and hypothesis testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send me an email if you are interested in seeing the evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ### Boston University Summer 2019

- [CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics](https://gianlucarusso.github.io/JMP/Syll_EC204_SMR2_2019.pdf) (Evaluations available upon request)

### Boston University Summer 2018

- [CAS EC 204 Empirical Economics](https://gianlucarusso.github.io/JMP/Syll_EC204_SMR2_2019.pdf) (Evaluations available upon request) --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAS EC 102 Introduction to Macroeconomics</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec102/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec102/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During Grad School I have been a teaching fellow for Introduction to Macroeconomics. I worked with Instructor Bruce Watson and my duties included teaching discussion sessions and grading exams. Send me an email for evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAS EC 201 Introduction to Microeconomics</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec201/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec201/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During my second year at BU I was also a teaching fellow for Introductory Micro. For this class I graded assignments, final exams and held office hours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CAS EC 371 Environmental Economics</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec371/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/classes/ec371/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During my second year at BU I was a teaching fellow for Environmental Economics. The class was taught by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/johannesschmieder/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Johannes Schmieder&lt;/a&gt;. My duties included teaching a review of analysis applied to economics, grading and holding office hours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/data/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resesarch</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/teaching/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
