<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Workinprogs | Gianluca Russo</title>
    <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Workinprogs</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/images/icon_hud3c4f4215db4e1df4afdcacbbae4761e_411935_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Workinprogs</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building States Through Restorative Justice</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/trc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/trc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  How do states rebuild nations after a major conflict? Truth and Reconciliation Commissions (TRCs) have emerged as one of the most common interventions to achieve this objective. Despite their popularity, little is known about their efficacy to foster reconciliation and nation-building. We fill this gap by studying the seminal TRC established in South Africa after the end of Apartheid. To measure exposure to TRC across South African municipalities, we leverage quasi random variation in media coverage of the TRC message. South African municipalities with higher historical exposure to TRC on media have lower levels of violence today. This effect is driven by improved nation-building and higher trust towards post-Apartheid institutions. Exploiting daily variation in TRC hearings and mediatic exposure in the short-run, we bolster our interpretation that our long-run results are forged in the years of the TRC activity. The same evidence suggests that our results are driven by the coverage of TRC on media as opposed to generic media exposure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ideology, Conformity and Performance</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/fasci_demia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/fasci_demia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 
## Abstract

&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  How do states rebuild nations after a major conflict? Truth and Reconciliation Commissions (TRCs) have emerged as one of the most common interventions to achieve this objective. Despite their popularity, little is known about their efficacy to foster reconciliation and nation-building. We fill this gap by studying the seminal TRC established in South Africa after the end of Apartheid. To measure exposure to TRC across South African municipalities, we leverage quasi random variation in media coverage of the TRC message. South African municipalities with higher historical exposure to TRC on media have lower levels of violence today. This effect is driven by improved nation-building and higher trust towards post-Apartheid institutions. Exploiting daily variation in TRC hearings and mediatic exposure in the short-run, we bolster our interpretation that our long-run results are forged in the years of the TRC activity. The same evidence suggests that our results are driven by the coverage of TRC on media as opposed to generic media exposure. --&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outmigration and Economic Development: Evidence from the Italian Mass Migration</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/outmigration/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workinprog/outmigration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  Does emigration affect economic development? We study this question in the context of the Italian mass emigration between 1884 and 1913, when twelve million Italians left the country.
We assemble a unique dataset at the municipality level, linking cumulative emigration rates to a number of indicators of economic development throughout the twentieth century.
Exploiting variation in the availability of information about the potential gains from migration before the start of mass migration, we construct an instrumental variable for the total emigration rate.
Results indicate that while instrumented cumulative emigration was balanced on population before the start of mass emigration, it had a negative, large, and highly persistent effect on short and long run population. Historical mass emigration also reduced educational attainment, income per capita and other proxies of economic development in the long run. Further, we show that emigration favored the expansion of the agricultural sector, at the expense of manufacturing. We speculate that selective emigration was a key mechanism behind our results.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
