<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Working Paper | Gianluca Russo</title>
    <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/tags/working-paper/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://gianlucarusso.github.io/tags/working-paper/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Working Paper</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/images/icon_hud3c4f4215db4e1df4afdcacbbae4761e_411935_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Working Paper</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/tags/working-paper/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>War, Socialism and the Rise of Fascism: An Empirical Exploration</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/wwi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/wwi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recent ascent of right-wing populist movements in many countries has rekindled interest in understanding the causes of the rise of Fascism in
inter-war years. In this paper, we argue that there was a strong link
between the surge of support for the Socialist Party after World War I and
the subsequent emergence of Fascism in Italy. We first develop a source of
variation in Socialist support across Italian municipalities in the 1919
election based on war casualties from the area. We show that these
casualties are unrelated to a battery of political, economic and social
variables before the war and had a major impact on Socialist support (partly
because the Socialists were the main anti-war political movement). Our main
result is that this boost to Socialist support (that is &amp;lsquo;exogenous&amp;rsquo; to the prior political leaning of the municipality) led to greater local Fascist activity as measured by local party branches and Fascist political violence (squadrismo), and to significantly larger vote share of the Fascist Party in the 1924 election. We document that the increase in the vote share of the Fascist Party was not
at the expense of the Socialist Party and instead came from right-wing
parties, thus supporting our interpretation that center-right and right-wing
voters coalesced around the Fascist Party because of the &amp;lsquo;red scare&amp;rsquo;. We also show that the veterans did not consistently support the Fascist Party and there is no evidence for greater nationalist sentiment in areas with more casualties. We provide evidence that landowner associations and greater presence of local elites played an important role in the rise of Fascism. Finally, we find greater likelihood of Jewish deportations in 1943-45 and lower vote share for Christian Democrats after WWII in areas with greater early Fascist activity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulating Child Labor: Evidence from the US Progressive Era</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/cll/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/cll/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1880 to 1920, child labor in the United States fell dramatically. At the same time, most states passed laws regulating minimum working ages and mandating compulsory schooling laws. Past quantitative work based on census samples have yielded mixed results on the efficacy of these laws and historians have questioned whether the politically powerful employers of children would allow such regulation if child labor was in high demand. Turning to the newly-digitized complete count census data from 1880, 1900, 1910, 1920, and 1930, we find large effects of child labor laws and compulsory schooling laws on child labor. While Progressive era legislation reduced labor supply from boys and girls in equal measure, the laws did had differential effects, binding in urban areas especially in the largest cities and more for the children of foreign-born parents. Children with parents working in manufacturing and textiles were especially affected by the labor restrictions.
In contrast to the reduction of labor supply among white children in urban areas, we find that legislation had mixed effects on the odds of children not explicitly targeted by the reformers, in particular rural white and black children.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mass Media and Cultural Assimilation: Broadcasting the American Dream on Radio</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/radio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/workingpapers/radio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does media shape culture? I leverage the expansion of radio networks in the United States to identify the impact of access to mass media on cultural assimilation and homogenization. I reconstruct radio network access via a signal propagation model suitable to AM radio, the only radio technology available at the time. I determine what radio channels were available to American households by feeding the propagation model with newly digitized data on the universe of transmitting stations during the interwar period. I combine radio network coverage with several measures of cultural change based on naming patterns for children. Exploiting exogenous variation in radio signal reception induced by soil characteristics and stations&amp;rsquo; tower growth over time, I provide evidence that network access homogenized American culture. Homogenization occurred through the assimilation of white immigrant and black households towards mainstream white native culture. Assimilation is strongest for immigrant families: foreign parents were six percent more likely to name their sons using popular white names after network access. Focusing on names from baseball players, I suggest that aspirational naming is a key mechanism to explain certain features of the results. While foreign households picked from the full distribution of baseball names, native families chose names exclusively from the most successful, those featured in the All-Star games. Thus, in addition to diffusing information, the radio has subtler effects, increasing the likelihood of &amp;ldquo;naming for success&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
