<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications | Gianluca Russo</title>
    <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Publications</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/images/icon_hud3c4f4215db4e1df4afdcacbbae4761e_411935_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building States Through Public Truth-Telling (2024)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/trc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/trc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  How do states rebuild after decades of institutionalized oppression, deep societal
trauma, and intergroup violence? We study the effect of one of the most iconic examples of transitional justice, the South African Truth and Reconciliation Commission (TRC), which attempted to rebuild South African society through public truth-telling. We reconstruct exposure to live broadcasting of the TRC across South African suburbs to generate quasi-exogenous variation in media coverage of the TRC hearings. We demonstrate that while the TRC fostered unity among Black South Africans, it also weakened interracial relations. In particular, we document increased segregation, lower interracial marriage rates, and reduced interracial trust. Additionally, we leverage administrative tax data to argue that the TRC hindered the implementation of affirmative action policies aimed at workplace integration. Finally, we suggest that these effects stem from Whites adjusting their beliefs about judicial bias: using daily variation in hearing content, we observe increased backlash among White South Africans whenever a White perpetrator is scrutinized by the court.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Socializing Alone: How Online Homophily Has Undermined Social Cohesion in the US (2024)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/facebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  Online social networks have changed how people interact across large distances. We examine the long-run effect of a key feature of these networks – online homophily – on interpersonal interactions in local communities. Using Facebook data, we measure online homophily across counties in the United States. To identify effects, we exploit a conflict between Facebook and Google over data sharing of user information in the early expansion phase of Facebook, which induced variation in the ability to connect with friends in socially similar counties. We find evidence that homophilic connections led to increased Facebook usage but reduced offline socialization, as measured by visits to bars, restaurants, and live sports events. The effects are substantial: we estimate that a one-standard deviation increase in online homophily led to a 60-70% long-run increase in social media usage and approximately a 25% reduction in offine socialization. This shift was accompanied by a deterioration of local social cohesion, as individuals became less connected across income strata and less likely to share the same political opinions with others in their counties. Overall, our results indicate that when a natural demand for connecting with socially similar people is met by the supply of a &#39;death-of-distance&#39; technology, it comes at the cost of social cohesion and traditional community bonds at the local level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Media and Assimilation: Evidence from the Golden Age of Radio (2024)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/radio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/radio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt; The advent of the radio networks in the early twentieth century marked the inception
of the first national media platform in US history. This development coincided
with the conclusion of the Age of Mass Migration, a historical period characterized by
record-high diversity within the US society. How did the sudden rise of national radio
networks affect the assimilation of millions of immigrants in the US? I answer this
question by building quasi-random variation in the initial expansion of radio networks
coverage. Through the application of a difference-in-difference design and leveraging
evidence from diverse samples, I document that higher exposure to radio networks
facilitated immigrant assimilation across various outcomes, including higher rates of
intermarriage with natives, increased naturalization, and a greater propensity to adopt
names that sounded less foreign. Additionally, I find that exposure to radio networks
led to enhanced English proficiency among recently arrived immigrants. I argue that a
key channel of assimilation was through the impact of role models on the media. Using
data on baseball, I show that immigrants perceived baseball players as media role
models of assimilation. Immigrant households were more likely to name their children
after baseball players who shared similar ancestral origins to them or who achieved
notable success during a season.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulating Child Labor: Evidence from the US Progressive Era (2020)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/cll/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/cll/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;  From 1880 to 1920, child labor in the United States fell dramatically. At the same time, most states passed laws regulating minimum working ages and mandating compulsory schooling laws. Past quantitative work based on census samples have yielded mixed results on the efficacy of these laws and historians have questioned whether the politically powerful employers of children would allow such regulation if child labor was in high demand. Turning to the newly-digitized complete count census data from 1880, 1900, 1910, 1920, and 1930, we find large effects of child labor laws and compulsory schooling laws on child labor. While Progressive era legislation reduced labor supply from boys and girls in equal measure, the laws did had differential effects, binding in urban areas especially in the largest cities and more for the children of foreign-born parents. Children with parents working in manufacturing and textiles were especially affected by the labor restrictions.
In contrast to the reduction of labor supply among white children in urban areas, we find that legislation had mixed effects on the odds of children not explicitly targeted by the reformers, in particular rural white and black children.
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
