<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications | Gianluca Russo</title>
    <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Publications</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/images/icon_hud3c4f4215db4e1df4afdcacbbae4761e_411935_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Media and Assimilation: Evidence from the Golden Age of Radio (2021)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/radio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/radio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I argue that exposure to mainstream mass media facilitates immigrants&amp;rsquo; assimilation. I exploit the rise and expansion of radio broadcasting in the United States after the Age of Mass Migration ended to identify the effect of radio exposure on immigrants&amp;rsquo; assimilation.
I reconstruct exogenous exposure to radio networks using a novel propagation model suitable to AM radio, the only radio technology available at the time.
Exploiting the US full count census, I find that radio networks had a strong effect on immigrants&amp;rsquo; assimilation. Immigrants exposed to radio networks exerted higher effort to assimilate by naming their children with less distinctively foreign names and by becoming US citizens more often. Exposure to US radio networks also increased the likelihood of marrying a US citizen from US-born parents. Using names from baseball players, I show that aspiration might have been a key mechanism to explain why radio promoted assimilation. Immigrant households named their children exclusively after players that performed particularly well during the season, suggesting they were &amp;lsquo;naming for success.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulating Child Labor: Evidence from the US Progressive Era (2020)</title>
      <link>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/cll/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gianlucarusso.github.io/publications/cll/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1880 to 1920, child labor in the United States fell dramatically. At the same time, most states passed laws regulating minimum working ages and mandating compulsory schooling laws. Past quantitative work based on census samples have yielded mixed results on the efficacy of these laws and historians have questioned whether the politically powerful employers of children would allow such regulation if child labor was in high demand. Turning to the newly-digitized complete count census data from 1880, 1900, 1910, 1920, and 1930, we find large effects of child labor laws and compulsory schooling laws on child labor. While Progressive era legislation reduced labor supply from boys and girls in equal measure, the laws did had differential effects, binding in urban areas especially in the largest cities and more for the children of foreign-born parents. Children with parents working in manufacturing and textiles were especially affected by the labor restrictions.
In contrast to the reduction of labor supply among white children in urban areas, we find that legislation had mixed effects on the odds of children not explicitly targeted by the reformers, in particular rural white and black children.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
